A Guide to the Fairfax County Office of Public Affairs Photograph Collection, 1962-2009
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Fairfax County Office of Public Affairs Photograph Collection, 1962-2009
Fairfax County Public Library
22 linear feet
The Fairfax County Office of Public Affairs Photograph Collection consists of 44 boxes containing millions of images spanning the years 1962-2009. Formats include 4x5 sheet film; 35mm negative film; 120 negative film; slides, contact sheets; photographic prints; and CD-ROMs.
Fairfax County Office of Public Affairs
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Collection transferred to the Virginia Room by the Fairfax County Office of Public Affairs on March 15, 2018.
Historical and Biographical Information
The Fairfax County Division of Information opened on March 1, 1962, with the primary function of enlightening the public about the county government’s operations. To carry out this function, the Information Office prepared and published regular annual and monthly reports, citizens handbooks, pamphlets, brochures, code sections, ordinances, departmental reports, and the Weekly Agenda newsletter. The division also wrote press releases and provided photographic needs for the county’s departments.
The Division of Information was originally based at the Fairfax Courthouse and supplemented in the 1960s by three substations in Groveton, McLean and Annandale. These substations also sold county auto tags, dog tags, maps, and studies to the public. In 1968, Elliot G. Shaw, Jr., the Director of Information Services, created the official flag for Fairfax County. The Board of Supervisors adopted the flag in June 1968, and it continues to be in county-wide use today.
In the fall of 1968, the Division of Information was reorganized and reconstituted as the Division of Public Affairs. The Board of Supervisors directed that the reorganized division assist county government officials with communication issues; make available a maximum amount of county government information and activities to the news media; create publications with essential information for citizens; respond to informational requests; and stimulate public interest in county government. Presently known as the Office of Public Affairs (OPA), the division is based in the Fairfax County Government Center and continues to be the hub for the county’s media operations.
Scope and Content
The Fairfax County Office of Public Affairs Photograph Collection consists of 44 boxes containing millions of images spanning the years 1962-2009. Formats include 4x5 sheet film; 35mm negative film; 120 negative film; slides, contact sheets; photographic prints; and CD-ROMs. Throughout the division’s history, the Office of Public Affairs (OPA) built a photo archive documenting county government events, meetings, ceremonies, people, places, and buildings. These images were used for a variety of purposes including publication in county newsletters, reports, and news releases. Beginning in the 1970s, the OPA began photographing presentations at every Board of Supervisors meeting. These included certificate and award presentations, proclamations, and other ceremonial happenings. The bulk of this collection consists of images from board presentations. Subjects include the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors, county agencies, employees, buildings, and events.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
Microfiched Office of Public Affairs news releases dating from 1968-1992 were removed, cataloged, and added to the Virginia Room’s microfiche collection.
Index Terms
Fairfax County (Va.); Fairfax County (Va.). Board of Supervisors; Fairfax County (Va.). Office of Public Affairs
Container List
- Series 1: Negatives, 1964-1971
  - Administration - Building and Grounds - Edward Houchins, Art Saffelle, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administration - Inserter in Mail Room. L to R. Mike DelMonte, Kenneth Lawson, Gerri Curtis, Nancy Sanderson, Ed Peatross, Bill Myers, 1970 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administration - John Ferguson, Archie Lewis. Mail bags - tax returns to go out, 1970 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administration - John Ferguson, Archie Lewis. Mail bags - tax returns to go out, 1970 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Administration - Mike DelMonte mail stacks, 1970 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Administration - Print Shop, 1969 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administration - Print Shop employees and press, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administration - Print Shop employees and press, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administration - Print Shop. C. Gauis[?] adjust camera used in mailing plate negatives, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administration - Radio repair shop (Communications), 1969 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administration - Radio Shop. "Communications". Carroll., Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Administration - Radio Shop. "Communications". Carroll., Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Animal Shelter - Two puppies [image used in Weekly Agenda], Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Assessments - Assessments Office [Pl + Fin Man], 1970 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Assessments - Assessments Office [Pl + Fin Man], 1970 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Assessments - Counter clerks and customers at Groveton Branch Assessments Office, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Assessments - Groveton Substation exterior, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Assessments - Groveton Substation exterior, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Assessments - John Ferguson, Supervisor of Assessments, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Assessments - McLean Assessments Office, Elm Street, exterior, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Assessments - Samuel Patteson, County real estate assessment chief demonstrating use of microfilm in the Assessment Office to Rafael Elster, director of Programa Central of Catastro Municipal in Caracas, Venezuela, 1971 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Assessments - Samuel Patteson, County real estate assessment chief demonstrating use of microfilm in the Assessment Office to Rafael Elster, director of Programa Central of Catastro Municipal in Caracas, Venezuela, 1971 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Beautification - Buick Motor Division 1970 Winner, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Beautification - Flora Johnson is given plaque by Chairman William S. Hoofnagle, 1971 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Beautification - Melpar - Route 50 - Winner of 1970 Beautification Award, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Beautification - Melpar - Route 50 - Winner of 1970 Beautification Award, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Beautification - Melpar - Route 50 - Winner of 1970 Beautification Award, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Beautification - Security Storage Co. Warehouse on Route 7 west of Tyson's - Winner of 1970 Beautification Award, 1970 June (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Board of Supervisors - Board honors Donald R. Bowman, 1971 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Board of Supervisors - Board honors Donald R. Bowman, 1971 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Board of Supervisors - Board moves to new building [Massey Building] - Mr. Babson, Mrs. Pennino, 1969 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Board of Supervisors - Board moves to new building [Massey Building] - Mr. Babson, Mrs. Pennino, 1969 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Board of Supervisors - Board of Supervisors group, 1970 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Board of Supervisors - Charles Majer, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Board of Supervisors - Harold Miller, 1971 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Board of Supervisors - Harold Miller, 1971 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Board of Supervisors - Harriet F. Bradley, McLean Plan, 1970 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Board of Supervisors - Helen Momsen, 1971 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Board of Supervisors - Helen Momsen, 1971 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Board of Supervisors - Herbert Harris and others - Harrelson Tract Deed, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Board of Supervisors - Herbert Harris and others - Harrelson Tract Deed, Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Board of Supervisors - Herbert Harris, Joseph Alexander, and Metro map, Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Board of Supervisors - Joseph Alexander office in Groveton Substation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Board of Supervisors - Joseph Alexander office in Groveton Substation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Board of Supervisors - Martha Pennino, Vice Chairman, 1969 January (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Board of Supervisors - Thomas B. Wright, 1967 December (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Board of Supervisors - Thomas B. Wright, 1969 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Board of Supervisors - Thomas B. Wright, 1969 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Board of Supervisors - Virginia McEnearney sworn in, 1971 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Board of Supervisors - William S. Hoofnagle, 1969 December (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Board of Supervisors - William S. Hoofnagle swearing in, 1969 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Board of Supervisors - William S. Hoofnagle sworn in by Judge Arthur Sinclair, 1971 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Board of Supervisors - William S. Hoofnagle sworn in by Judge Arthur Sinclair, 1971 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Board of Supervisors - William S. Hoofnagle, H.O. Miller, 1971 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Board of Supervisors - William S. Hoofnagle, H.O. Miller, 1971 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Building Maintenance - Carpenter Shop custodial help - George, Charlie, Ed, Jackson, James, Evelyn, Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Building Maintenance - Carpenter Shop custodial help - George, Charlie, Ed, Jackson, James, Evelyn, Undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Building Maintenance - Carpenter Shop custodial help - George, Charlie, Ed, Jackson, James, Evelyn, Undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Chairman - William S. Hoofnagle with Animal Shelter lady, Undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Chairman - William S. Hoofnagle with Gov. Linwood Holton, Undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Clifton - Clifton Council and Mayor sworn in. L to R. Mrs. Cora Smith, Mrs. Nellie Fairfax, Miss Phyllis Waters, Julian W. Burke, Woodrow W. Caples, Ronans Skujins, Mrs. Barbara J. Breen, Ded Clk., Mrs. Martha V. Pennino, 1970 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Communication - Civil Defense Emergency Operation Center - Administrative Area, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Communication - Civil Defense Emergency Operation Center - Auxiliary Generator, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Communication - Civil Defense Emergency Operation Center - Communication Center, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Communication - Civil Defense Emergency Operation Center - Kitchen, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Communication - Civil Defense Emergency Operation Center - Medical Emergency Room, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Communication - Civil Defense Emergency Operation Center - Outside exit and decontamination station at foot of stairs, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Communication - Civil Defense Emergency Operation Center - Restrooms, 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Communication - Emergency Operating Center, 1970 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Communication - Print Shop in Court House - Bill Myers (standing) goes over material with Bob Hood at the varityper in the composition room, 1970 July (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Communication - Print Shop in Court House - Ken Lawson and Norman Williams put material in camera frame to shoot negative of copy, 1970 July (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Communication - Print Shop in Court House - L to R. John Williams, Dave Gough and Ed Peatross at their presses, which turned out nearly seven million impressions last year, 1970 July (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Communication - Print Shop in Court House - Mrs. Nancy Sanderson (on left) and Gerry Curtis operate the quick copy section and addressograph machine, 1970 July (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Communication - Print Shop in Court House - Print Shop Supervisor Charlie Garris goes over work order with Mrs. Phyllis Martz at the collating machine, 1970 July (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Community Services - Burgundy Community Center [Cameron School Park], 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Community Services - John Grinnell, Mrs. Peg Poulton, McLean Community Center, 1971 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Community Services - John Grinnell, William S. Hoofnagle, Martha Pennino, Fred Allen, Braddock Community Center, 1970 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Community Services - John R. Grinnell, 1969 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Cooperative Extension - Agricultural Agent John L. Gugino examines plant specimen for disease symptoms, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Cooperative Extension - Charles Hall, new County Agent, Undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - County Development - Barbara Dorr puts finishing touches on a model, Undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - County Development - Donald Strickhooser, County Development, 1971 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - County Development - Draftsman Katherine Cardin keeps map overlays up to date, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - County Development - Highway signs graphic arts, 1971 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - County Development - James Pammel and York Phillips, Land Use, 1971 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - County Development - Lake Braddock (Filling), 1970 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - County Development - Lake Braddock Empty, 1970 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - County Development - Mapping Division personnel - Dorothy Wolf and Ed Thayer in the Graphics Branch, 1970 August (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - County Development - Mapping Division personnel - L to R: Fred Beales, Mrs. Kathy Cardin, Bill Sprouse and Roy Clancy in the Overlay Branch, 1970 August (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - County Development - Mapping Division personnel - L to R: Janice Downey, Doug Smith and John Whitmer in the Large Area Map Branch, 1970 August (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - County Development - Mapping Division personnel - L to R: Roger Smith, Bill Krennerich, Mrs. Sharon Puckett, Duane Rowley, Mike Hogge and Herman Shubin in the Property Map Branch, 1970 August (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - County Development - Mapping Division personnel - Paul Marseglia in the Large Area Map Branch, 1970 August (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - County Development - Maps - old Planning and Zoning picture, Undated (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - County Development - Plumbing inspectors, 1971 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - County Development - Survey Tower (Mapping Division of County Development), 1969 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - County Development - Zoning signs [man installing zoning signs on property], Undated (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - County Executive - County Executive Carlton C. Massey, Deputy County Executive John V. Berberich III Deputy County Executive George J.Kelly Jr. in new Board Room with county seal behind, 1969 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - County Executive - George J. Kelley Jr., 1970 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - County Executive - George J. Kelley Jr. meeting with Plant Supervisors, Union Officers and Shop Stewarts from the Operations Division outlining plans for the Lower Potomac Plant. L to R: Ray Hutchins, Mick Stone, George J. Kelley Jr., Bob Seymour, Butch Foutz, Raymond Menke, 1971 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - County Executive - George J. Kelley Jr. sworn in by Frank Gooding, 1971 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - County Executive - George Kelly, Deputy County Executive, 1968 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - County Executive - Gilda Harris, 1971 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - County Executive - Howard G. Borgstrom, 1971 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - County Executive - James P. McDonald, 1971 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - County Executive - Jay Lambeth, 1971 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - County Executive - John Berberich and George J. Kelley Jr., Undated (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - County Executive - John V. Berberich III, 1970 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - County Executive - John V. Berberich III, Deputy County Executive, Undated (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - County Executive - John V. Berberich III, Deputy County Executive, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Court House - Arched walkway, Undated (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Court House - Daniel Chichester portrait from Court House, Undated (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Court House - Exterior, Undated (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Court House - Exterior / Winter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Court House - Exterior / Winter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Court House - Front, Undated (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Court House - Front lawn construction, 1967 December (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Court House - Front of old section with cannon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Court House - Judge Paul E. Brown oil portrait, Undated (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Court House - Juvenile and Domestic Relations, Undated (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Court House - Old Court House, Undated (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Court House - Old Court House, Matthew Brady pic c. 1863, Undated (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Court House - Old Court House, restored court room, Undated (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Court House - Old Court House, restored court room, Undated (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Court House - Old Court House, restored court room, Undated (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Court House - Old section thru arch, Undated (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Court House - Old section thru arch, Undated (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Court House - Old section thru arch, Undated (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Court House - Record Room "Deed Books", Undated (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Court House - Rededication of old Fairfax Courthouse, Undated (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Court House - Restored Courtroom, Undated (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Court House - Side view with cannon and Marr monument, Undated (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - Court House - Side view with railing, Undated (Box 1, Folder 132)
  - Court House - Snow scenes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Court House - Washington's Will, clerk of courts office, Undated (Box 1, Folder 134)
  - Courts - Arthur Sinclair, senior judge, 1970 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 135)
  - Courts - County Attorney, 1969 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 136)
  - Courts - County Attorney Donald Stevens, 1970 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 137)
  - Courts - County Attorney Donald C. Stevens, 1968 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 138)
  - Courts - Dexter Odin (new) Ralph Louk (old) being sworn in Clerk of the Court taking seat at board table with Commonwealth Attorney (Robert E. Lee's picture on wall), Undated (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Courts - Donald C. Crounse, judge, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 140)
  - Courts - Frank Deierhoi, judge, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Courts - Frank Gooding swearing in, Undated (Box 1, Folder 142)
  - Courts - Frank Gooding, Clerk of the Courts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 143)
  - Courts - Frank Gooding, William S. Hoofnagle, Eleanor Chesley, Undated (Box 1, Folder 144)
  - Courts - Juvenile Court Record Room, Undated (Box 1, Folder 145)
  - Courts - Juvenile Court, Judge Frank Deierhoi, Undated (Box 1, Folder 146)
  - Courts - Record Room for Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court, Undated (Box 1, Folder 147)
  - Courts - Robert Horan, Commonwealth's Attorney, 1970 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 148)
  - Courts - Robert Horan, Commonwealth's Attorney at desk, 1968 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 149)
  - Courts - Robert Horan, Commonwealth's Attorney receiving award, 1969 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 150)
  - Courts - Robert Horan, Commonwealth's Attorney sworn in as C.C. by T. Chapman clerk, Undated (Box 1, Folder 151)
  - Data Processing - Computers in office, 1970 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 152)
  - Data Processing - Computers in office, Undated (Box 1, Folder 153)
  - Data Processing - Data Processing tax bill scraps, Mrs. Sarah Prevatte, 1969 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 154)
  - Data Processing - Fairfax County Data Processing, 1969 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 155)
  - Data Processing - IBM 1401, Undated (Box 1, Folder 156)
  - Data Processing - Mr. Edward Long, Chief of Computer Operations, checks the status of the IBM 360/40 computer while Mrs. Libby Hutchison updates the computer schedule board. Mrs. Leslie Nanny is carrying a reel of magnetic tape from storage to the computer, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 157)
  - Data Processing - Mrs. Jane Luzader removes a reel of magnetic tape from the county's EDP library. This one reel contains the names, addresses and precincts of the county's 124,200 registered voters. Before this information was recorded on type, it occupied 40 drawers of 3 1/4 x 7 3/8 inch cards, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 158)
  - Data Processing - Mrs. Jane Luzader tests a real estate inquiry program on an IBM 2260 Display terminal. A number of these terminals will be installed in the new County Building to provide rapid response to inquiries on the 113,388 parcels of land in Fairfax County. The same terminals will permit the Real Estate Division to enter new information directly into remotely located computer files., 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 159)
  - Data Processing - Mrs. Leslie Nanny, Programmer Trainee, and Harlan Stillwell Sr., Senior Programmer operate the IBM 360/40 computer. She feeds instructions to the computer via the console typewriter while he inserts a disk pack containing 29,176,000 characters of information into the IBM 2314 Direct A[?] Storage Facility. The county's [?] and estate file is stored on three of these disk packs. The computer can retrieve a taxpayer's record in less than one-tenth of a second to display information visually or print bills or other data., 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 160)
  - Data Processing - Mrs. Leslie Nanny, Programmer Trainee, time-stamps a job ticket at the IBM 360/40 computer console while Charles Parsons, computer operator, inserts a new disk file into the IBM 2314 Direct Access Storage Facility. The computer simultaneously is processing student scheduling for the Public School System and accident analysis for the Police Department in a multiprogrammed enviornment, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 161)
  - Data Processing - Mrs. Libby Hutchison and Mrs. Beverly Davis key punch operators, operate IBM 2260 Display Terminals, checking names and addresses on state income tax forms to determine whether individuals are listed in the computer file of more than 150,000 entries. This teleprocessing application saved more than $6,000 in data collection costs and speeded up the process by five weeks. The computer was processing the county's monthly payroll while three operators were making their unrelate inquiries, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 162)
  - Data Processing - Mrs. Rozelle Costello delivers computer job control cards and a magnetic tape of Welfare data to computer operator Jack Ellis. The information on the tape will be used to prepare authorizations to purchase food stamps. This is done twice a month for more than 1,400 recipients, at the rate of 100 per minute., 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 163)
  - EMTA (Equipment Management Transportation Agency) - County Garage, 1969 October (Box 1, Folder 164)
  - EMTA (Equipment Management Transportation Agency) - County Garage, 1969 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 165)
  - EMTA (Equipment Management Transportation Agency) - Groveton Garage [bowling alley in background], 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 166)
  - EMTA (Equipment Management Transportation Agency) - Jermantown Garage, 1969 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 167)
  - EMTA (Equipment Management Transportation Agency) - Mrs. Margaret Gerber, EMTA motor pool dispatching clerk, 1971 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 168)
  - Fairfax Coat of Arms - Fairfax County Coat of Arms, Undated (Box 1, Folder 169)
  - Fairfax Coat of Arms - Seal with Town Crier, Undated (Box 1, Folder 170)
  - Fairfax House - Before opening - exterior, Undated (Box 1, Folder 171)
  - Fairfax House - Before opening - interior - dining area, Undated (Box 1, Folder 172)
  - Fairfax House - Before opening - interior - living room, Undated (Box 1, Folder 173)